A Guide to the Cumming Family Papers
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #6922-ae
Cumming Family Papers 1864-1986
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
6922-ae
ca. 2,000 items
Hugh Smith Cumming, Jr.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
These papers were bequeathed to the Library by Hugh S. Cumming, Jr., and were delivered by Ms. Diana C. Kendrick of Washington, D.C. on March 21, 1988.
Scope and Content
This addition to the papers of Ambassador Hugh S. Cumming, Jr.(1900-1986) consists of ca. 2,000 items (7 Hollinger boxes, ca. 3 linear feet), 1864-1986, and includes photographs, photograph albums, memorabilia, scrapbooks, slides, certificates, passports, diaries, correspondence, a law course notebook from the University of Virginia, genealogical material, legal papers, printed material, and a memorial album for Winifred B. Cumming(1907-1978).
The collection has been separated into three different types of material: miscellaneous papers, bound volumes, and photographs. The photographs comprise the largest amount of material.
The miscellaneous papers include certificates; correspondence; the Ft. Monroe Coast Artillery School Gunnery Bulletins (1918); genealogical material; gunnery notes and related printed material; the High School Cadet Corps Papers of Hugh Smith Cumming, Jr.; legal papers; a memorial album for Winifred Burney West Cumming; memorabilia; a report entitled, "Owners of `the Grove' from 1839-1906 ( Thomas Wynne through Dr. E. G. Booth)" by Lou Powers; newsclippings; and papers concerning the Washington Cathedral Association College of Church Musicians.
The correspondence is generally of a personal nature consisting of congratulatory letters upon Hugh Cumming, Jr.'s engagement to Winifred B. West and letters from family and friends. An exception is an electrostatic copy of a letter from George Kennan to Elbridge Durbow, November 10, 1980, discussing their differences of opinion on foreign policy. There is also a folder of correspondence between Cumming and various University of Virginia officials.
Legal papers include Winifred B. Cumming Trust material and copies of the wills of Birne T. West, Winifred B. Cumming, Hugh S. Cumming, Jr., and Edwin G. Booth(photostat).
The bound volumes include several printed works; diaries of Hugh S. Cumming, Jr., 1913, 1931-1932, 1945, and diaries/memorandum books, 1946, 1965-1983, 1985; and a law lecture course notebook.
Photographs, photograph albums, and slides include those from Cumming's service as Ambassador to Indonesia, 1953-1957; photographs of the Cumming and related families; " Carter's Grove" and " Overlook"; the Cummings in Europe and South America; European Scenes (1919, 1935-1936); Cumming at the Virginia Military Institute; vacation scenes; and the World War I Era.
Oversize material includes photographs, a map of Tierra del Fuego, and a Virginia Military Institute Memorabilia Scrapbook.
Container List
- SERIES I: MISCELLANEOUS PAPERS
  - Certificates, 1868-1986 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1922-1958, 1972-1984, n.d. (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence with the University of Virginia, 1979-1986 (Box Box 1)
  - Ft. Monroe Coast Artillery School: Gunnery Bulletins (4 folders), 1918 (Box Box 1)
  - Genealogical Material, 1931-1979, n.d. (Box Box 2)
  - Gunnery Notes and Related Printed Material, ca. 1918 (Box Box 2)
  - High School Cadet Corps Papers of Hugh Cumming, Jr., 1916-1917 (Box Box 2)
  - Legal Papers, 1957-1983 (Box Box 2)
  - Legal Papers: Passports, 1953-1968 (Box Box 2)
  - Legal Papers: Winifred B. Cumming Trust Material, 1976-1980 (Box Box 2)
  - Memorial Album for Winifred Burney West Cumming, 1907-1978, Volumes I & II (2 folders), 1977-1978 (Box Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Material, 1900-1979, n.d. (Box Box 3)
  - "Owners of `the Grove' from 1839-1906 ( Thomas Wynne through Dr. E.G. Booth)" by Lou Powers, 1984 May (Box Box 3)
  - Printed Material, 1931-1975, n.d. (Box Box 3)
  - Virginia Military Institute Memorabilia, 1918-1919 (Box Box 3)
  - Washington Cathedral Association: College of Church Musicians, 1961-1966, n.d. (Box Box 3)
- SERIES II: BOUND VOLUMES
  - Dinner Book kept by Winifred Cumming, 1948 (Box Box 3)
  - Lecture Notebook re Code Pleading from lectures in the University of Virginia Law School, 1922 (Box Box 3)
  - Log Book kept by Hugh Cumming, Jr. for his yacht San Joaquin in Sweden, 1944-1951 (Box Box 3)
  - The Knights of the Horse-Shoe by Dr. William A. Caruthers, 1881 (Box Box 3)
  - Directory of the Zeta Psi Fraternity, 1926 (Box Box 4)
  - Legends of Lands End by Claude O. Lanciano, Jr., 1971 (Box Box 4)
  - Walk a Little Faster Escape from Burma with General Stilwell in 1942 by Henrietta Thompson, 1980 (Box Box 4)
  - Letter Register, 1919 (Box Box 4)
  - Diaries of Hugh Cumming, Jr., 1913, 1931-1932, 1945 (Box Box 4)
  - Diaries/Memoranda Books of Hugh Cumming, Jr., 1946, 1965-1983, 1985 (Box Box 4)
- SERIES III: PHOTOGRAPHS
  - SUBSERIES A: INDONESIA
    - Photograph Album re the Presentation of Hugh Cumming, Jr. to President Sukarno as Ambassador of the United States to Indonesia, 1953 (Box Box 5)
    - Photograph Album: Indonesia, ca. 1953-1957 (Box Box 5)
    - Photograph Album: Visit of U.S. Vice-President Richard M. Nixon to Indonesia, ca. 1953 (Box Box 5)
    - Photographs: Indonesia Miscellaneous, ca. 1953-1957 (Box Box 5)
    - Photographs: Indonesian Receptions and Embassy Duties (2 folders), ca. 1953-1957 (Box Box 5)
    - Photographs: Indonesian Transparencies, ca. 1953-1957 (Box Box 5)
    - Photographs: Visit of Indonesian President Sukarno to the United States, [1956 ?] (Box Box 5)
    - Photographs: Visit of U.S. Vice-President Richard M. Nixon to Indonesian President Sukarno, ca. 1953 (Box Box 6)
    - Slides: Indonesia, ca. 1954-1957; (2 folders) (Box Box 6)
  - SUBSERIES B: MISCELLANEOUS
    - Photograph Album: Childhood Memory Book of Hugh Cumming, Jr., 1900-1926 (Box Box 6)
    - Photograph Album: Hugh S. Cumming, Jr.- Early Photographs, ca. 1920's (Box Box 6)
    - Photographs: " Carter's Grove" and " Overlook", 1933, 1962-1978, n.d. (Box Box 6)
    - Photographs: Cumming Family and Related Families (2 folders), 1864-1982, n.d. (Box Box 6)
    - Photographs: the Cummings in Europe and South America, ca. 1933-1950 (Box Box 7)
    - Photographs: European Scenes, 1919, 1935-1936 (Box Box 7)
    - Photographs: Miscellaneous, ca. 1915-1982, n.d. (Box Box 7)
    - Photographs: Virginia Military Institute, ca. 1918 (Box Box 7)
    - Photographs: World War I Era, ca. 1917-1919 (Box Box 7)
    - Slides: Vacation Scenes (2 folders), n.d. (Box Box 7)
    - Home Movie: Motion picture, "Eva's Baby," includes various family scenes, 16mm B & W, no sound, 4 inch reel (Othercontainertype Home Movie (F-283))
    - Home Movie: 1954, Motion picture, visit to a military outpost in Indo-China, 16 mm color, no sound, 4 inch reel (Othercontainertype Home Movie (F-284))
    - Virginia Military Institute Memorabilia Scrapbook (Pages removed from scrapbook), ca. 1918-1919 (Box Oversize Box S-19)
    - Map of Tierra del Fuego, 1967 (Box Oversize Box S-19)
    - Sketch & Photograph of Hugh Cumming, Jr., n.d. (Box Oversize Box S-19)
    - Six Unidentified Photographs of Group Settings, n.d. (Box Oversize Box S-19)
    - Photograph of the Junior Plattsburg Military Training Camp, Fort Terry, Plum Island, Long Island Sound, 1916 (Box Oversize Box S-19)